Harvard University. Corporation. Records of land and property owned by Harvard University, 1643-1835: an inventory
Records of land and property owned by Harvard University, 1643-1835
- XVII. Winchendon, 1784-1808, .26 cubic feet (26 legal folders)
  Although numerous Harvard publications cite Royall's land donations as constituting 2,100+ acres, the records related to Winchendon and Granby lands in this collection suggest that the bequest was perhaps smaller in size.
  - Memorandum about sales of Royalston (Winchendon) lands, 1782-1784, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 43
  - Quitclaim deed for land in Winchendon, William Whitney to the President and Fellows of Harvard College, Jan. 30, 1787, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 44
  - Account of costs of repurchasing land in Winchendon from William Whitney, Jan. 1787, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 45
  - Letter from Abel Wilder to Ebenezer Storer about Winchendon land, May 17, 1787, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 46
    Wilder wrote to inform Storer that a man named Matthew Knight was interested in buying or leasing a portion of lot 104 in Winchendon.
  - Letter from Abel Wilder to Ebenezer Storer about Winchendon land, Dec. 7, 1787 and draft of Storer’s reply, Feb. 5, 1788, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 47
  - Letter from Abel Wilder to Ebenezer Storer about Winchendon land, April 5, 1788, and summary of Storer’s reply, May 17, 1788, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 48
  - John Butterick’s offer to purchase Winchendon land, July 5, 1788, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 49
  - Manuscript copy of court records related to Clark Chandler and Charles Chandler’s request for the partition of Winchendon land, Dec. 6, 1791, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 50
    Clark and Charles Chandler were entitled to one fourth of the land, through inheritance (John Chandler), and they took legal procedures to secure their portion.
  - Ebenezer Storer’s request that Daniel Forbes determine the location and value of the Winchendon land, March 14, 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 51
  - Letter from Daniel Forbes to Ebenezer Storer about Winchendon and Granby lands, March 26, 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 52
  - Letter from Simon Houghton, Jr. to Ebenezer Storer about choosing a different surveyor for Winchendon land, Sept. 3, 1796, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 53
    Houghton thought that Forbes was too unfamiliar with the land, and had to travel too far, to do an effective job surveying it.
  - Letter from Elisha Tucker expressing interest in purchasing Winchendon land, Jan. 23, 1797, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 54
  - Letter from William Robbins to Ebenezer Storer about Winchendon land, April 30, 1799, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 55
    Robbins informed Storer that a man named Levi Haywood claimed to own 93 acres of the land given to Harvard by Royall and had a deed to that effect, created in 1785. Robbins claimed that the original lot was 200 acres in size, and he offered to buy the 107 acres that were not claimed by Haywood.
  - Letter from Simon Houghton, Jr. to Ebenezer Storer about Winchendon land, June 29, 1799, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 56
  - Plan and description of Winchendon land, created by surveyor Moses Hale, June 15, 1801, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 57
    In this plot, the land is 133 acres in size.
  - Letter from Samuel Crosby to Ebenezer Storer about Winchendon land, June 28, 1806, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 58
    Crosby wrote to tell Storer that the bearer of his letter, Silvanus Boynton, was interested in purchasing the land and was a trustworthy man.
  - Silvanus Boynton’s offer to purchase Winchendon land, July 2, 1806, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 59
  - Letter from Benjamin May and David Beaman to Ebenezer Storer offering to purchase Winchendon land, July 6, 1806, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 60
  - Letter from Silvanus Boynton to Ebenezer Storer about purchasing Winchendon land, Sept. 25, 1806, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 61
  - Memoranda regarding individuals interested in purchasing Winchendon land, ca. 1806, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 62
    Interested parties included David Beaman, Daniel Butterick, and Daniel Boynton.
  - Letter from David Gooderidge to Ebenezer Storer offering to purchase Winchendon land, and memorandum about his offer, ca. 1806, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 63
  - Letter from Benjamin May, David Beaman, and Eliot Payson to William Whitney offering to purchase Winchendon land, May 23, 1807 with draft of Jonathan Jackson’s reply, June 1807, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 64
    The men wrote to William Whitney, whom they asked to convey their message to the new College treasurer, Jonathan Jackson. Jackson agreed to sell them the land and outlined the terms of sale.
  - Letter from Benjamin May, David Beaman, and Eliot Payson to Jonathan Jackson about appraising the Winchendon land, July 27, 1807, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 65
  - Memorandum about selection of appraisers for Winchendon land, Aug. 6, 1807, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 66
  - Appraisers’ return on the value of Winchendon land, Aug. 12, 1807, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 67
    The appraisers (Silas Holman, Jonathan Osgood and William Whitney) valued the lot of 133 acres at $6.33 per acre. Verso contains Jonathan Jackson’s memorandum about the specifics of the sale, written Aug. 27, 1807.
  - Memorandum about terms of sale of Winchendon land, March 1, 1808, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 68
  - Bond for a deed to Winchester land, President and Fellows of Harvard College to Benjamin May, Eliot Payson, and David Beaman, March 1, 1808, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 69
- XVIII. Stoughton's Pasture, 1786-1803, .07 cubic feet (5 legal folders and 1 oversize folder)
  Former Massachusetts Governor William Stoughton (1631-1701) gave a Dorchester pasture "20 acres ¾ 22 rods" in size to the College; this bequest was finalized in 1702, the year after his death, and the land was thenceforward called Stoughton's Pasture. Stoughton specified that income from the land, along with the income from Stoughton's Marsh (See Series XV), should be used to finance scholarships "in the first place, to a scholar of the town of Dorchester, and if there be none such, to one of the town of Milton, and if in want of such, then to any other well deserving, that shall be most needy."
  This series includes records related to Stoughton's Pasture, including an assessor's valuation of the land, records related to the sale of trees from the pasture, a surveyor's plan of the land, minutes for a lease, and a letter about the property's boundaries.
  - Assessor’s valuation of rent of Stoughton’s Pasture, April 15, 1786, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 70
    Assessment was sent to Ebenezer Storer by Samuel Coolidge, Town Clerk of Dorchester.
  - James Baker’s account of trees sold from Stoughton’s Pasture, May 26, 1794, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 71
  - Receipt from Ebenezer Storer to James Baker, for sale of trees from Stoughton’s Pasture, May 26, 1794, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 72
  - Plan of Stoughton’s Pasture, drawn by surveyor Mather Withington, May 24, 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 9, Folder 17
  - Minutes for a lease of Stoughton’s Pasture to Samuel Withington for 100 years, June 1, 1796, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 73
    Minutes indicate that Withington was to pay $835, presumably to cover the entire 100 years.
  - Letter from Thaddeus M. Harris to Ebenezer Storer about the boundaries of Stoughton’s Pasture, Aug. 24, 1803, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 74
- XIX. Granby, 1794-1798, .09 cubic feet (9 legal folders)
  In addition to the Winchendon lands (See Series XVII), prominent colonist Isaac Royall also bequeathed land located in Granby, Massachusetts to Harvard, for the creation of a Royall Professorship of Law. This land, estimated at between 800 and 900 acres in size, came into Harvard's possession after Royall died of smallpox in 1781. Records in this series include offers from various individuals to purchase the land, correspondence about its value and about trespassers, a surveyor's plan and description of the land, and minutes for the conveyance of the land to Joseph Eastman, who purchased it in 1796. The records also include Eastman's bond to the President and Fellows of Harvard College.
  Although numerous Harvard publications cite Royall's land donations as constituting 2,100+ acres, the records in this collection related to Winchendon and Granby lands suggest that the bequest was perhaps smaller in size.
  - Letter from Daniel Forbes (to Ebenezer Storer?) offering to purchase College land in Granby, Dec. 20, 1794, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 75
  - Letter from Simeon Strong to Ebenezer Storer about Granby land, Feb. 22, 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 76
    Storer appears to have asked Strong to assess the value of the land in Granby, which he didn’t feel he could do in the winter.
  - Plan and description of Granby land, created by surveyor Justus Dwight, March 12, 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 77
  - Letter from Daniel Forbes to the Harvard Corporation regarding his wish to purchase College land in Granby, March 14, 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 78
  - Letter from Simeon Strong to Ebenezer Storer about trespassers on Granby land, and the value of the land, March 19, 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 79
    Strong informed Storer that, among the settlers on the Granby land, only one man appeared to own a title to the land: Dr. Vinton, whose title was allegedly from 1778.
  - Letters from Joseph Eastman to Ebenezer Storer about Granby land, May 18, 1795 and Aug. 11, 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 80
  - Minutes for the conveyance of Granby land to Joseph Eastman, ca. Aug. 1795, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 81
  - Bond of Joseph Eastman to the President and Fellows of Harvard College, Jan. 30, 1796, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 82
    Signed by Joseph Eastman, Moses Bliss, and Simeon Strong.
  - Letter from Joseph Eastman to Ebenezer Storer about payment for Granby land, March 22, 1798, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 83
- XX. Other lands, 1647-1830, .30 cubic feet (18 legal folders and 6 oversize folders)
  The records in this series pertain to a variety of properties belonging to the College. In many instances, the circumstances surrounding the lands' becoming College property are not known, and the records appear to be incomplete. Some documents in this series were apparently compiled as summaries of dealings at numerous properties and thus refer to lands represented in other series of this collection; they are placed in this series because they pertain to multiple properties and were not records compiled in the course of managing those individual properties. This series consists of deeds, committee appointments, reports, memoranda, a writ of execution, a letter of attorney, a lease, and property valuations. These records pertain to lands in Andover, "Pequot country," Boston, Cambridge, Charlestown, Concord, Lincoln, Bedford, Lancaster, Newburyport, Menotomy, Woburn, Boxborough, Rumney Marsh, and a property called "the Gore" in western Massachusetts.
  - Manuscript copy of “Mr. Ward’s” conveyance of 600 acres of land “near Andover by Merrimake” to Harvard College on Dec. 10, 1646, copied in 1647, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 84
    Mr. Ward was the Reverend Nathaniel Ward.
  - Deed of gift from John Newgate to Harvard College of £5 annually “for ever” from revenues of his Rumney Marsh farm, June 11, 1650, UAI 15.750 Box 8, Folder 36
    Annotation on verso indicates that gift was entered into Suffolk County records of deeds, March 15, 1702.
  - General Court’s appointment of committee to consider Harvard’s land concerns, Oct. 20, 1663, and Court’s initial response to the committee’s findings, May 18, 1664, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 85
    The committee consisted of Francis Willoughby, Daniel Gookin, Richard Russell, Thomas Danforth, Zachariah Syms, and Jonathan Mitchell. The Court response refers to the 600 acres from Mr. Ward.
  - Deed of gift from Theodore Atkinson to the President and Fellows of Harvard College for land near Boston, Oct. 13, 1671, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 86
    According to Josiah Quincy's The History of Harvard University, Harvard ultimately “obtained nothing” from this gift.
  - Deed of mortgage for land near the Mill Bridge in Boston, from William Smith and Martha Smith to John Richards, (unknown month) 19, 1686/7, UAI 15.750 Box 9, Folder 18
    Richards was Harvard's Treasurer, and he bequeathed this mortgage and another one to Harvard. They became the possessions of the College when Richards died in 1694. Notes on verso from 1687, 1694, 1708, 1714/15, and 1716, including one from Harvard Treasurer John White. Deed explains that the land in question was occupied by tenant Henry Godfrey and bounded on the SE by a highway leading from Mill Bridge “towards the second meeting house”; that William Smith was a cordwainer; and that Richards gave the Smiths £58 in exchange for the deed of mortgage.
  - Deed of mortgage for land near Roxbury Gate in Boston, from Seth Perry and Dorothy Perry to John Richards, June 28, 1693, UAI 15.750 Box 9, Folder 19
    Recto signed by Seth Perry, Dorothy Perry, Jeremiah Dummer, Benjamin Eliott, Eliezer Moody, and Joseph Webb. Verso is annotated by the executors of the estate of Harvard Treasurer John Richards (Anne Richards, John Foster, Josiah Eldridge, and William Gill). This mortgage, and the repayments of Richards’ initial loan to the Perrys, was bequeathed to Harvard and came into the College's possession when Richards died in 1694.
  - Memorandum about various tracts of land and property belonging to Harvard College, 1646-1696, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 87
    Includes information about Nathaniel Ward’s gift of 600 acres, the Pequot lands, a gift from a Mr. Dodridge, and a gift from Major R. Sedgwick of “two small shops in Boston,” which was somehow transformed into a ship tavern owned by William Phillips, who in turn paid £20 per year in “rent.”
  - Manuscript extracts of deeds and other records regarding gifts of land to Harvard College, 1650-1719, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 88
    Includes extracts from wills of Samuel Sewall (Merriconeag Neck and Narragansett farm), John Newgate (Rumney Marsh), John Coggan (Coggan’s Marsh), Samuel Ward (Ward’s Island), and Theodore Atkinson (land near Boston), as well as donations made by the Proprietors of Rutland and the General Court.
  - Manuscript copy of grants of Cambridge land, given by the Proprietors of Common Lands in Cambridge to Harvard College, 1662-1724, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 89
    Note on verso: “Records of some of the College Lands in Cambridge Recd from Mr. Andrew Bordman Town Clerk of Cambridge. July 25, 1727.”
  - Nicholas Sever and Edward Wigglesworth’s report on College lands at Menotomy, March 20, 1726/7, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 90
    The tenants at Menotomy were Mr. Hill and Mr. Swan.
  - Writ of execution against property of Jonathan Procter and James Procter, on behalf of Thomas Hubbard, Jan. 27, 1753, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 91
    Notes on verso indicate that Woburn land belonging to the Procters (9 acres) was appraised and seized on Feb. 7, 1753. The appraisers were Benjamin Johnson, James Fowle, and John Turner. Middlesex County Sheriff Richard Foster notes that he was unable to locate any additional property belonging to the Procters. Other notes on the verso indicate that the lot was sold to John Caldwell.
  - Letter of attorney from the President and Fellows of Harvard College to Theophilus Parsons, April 7, 1800, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 92
    Signed by Joseph Willard.
  - Memorandum regarding Elijah Rice’s offer to purchase College lot between Westminster and Fitchburg (Massachusetts) called the Gore, Aug. 25, 1809, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 93
    This lot of land (250 acres) is possibly the one granted to the College after it was acknowledged that their lot in Townsend was actually in New Hampshire.
  - Lease of “house and lot in Cambridge called No. 5” to William Brown, March 31, 1812, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 94
    The house and lot rented to Brown are described as being “opposite the [Harvard] President’s house” and formerly occupied by Levi Hedge. Annotations indicate receipt of rent payments from 1812-1816. Signed by John Davis and William Brown.
  - Valuation of Oliver Wood and Alden Wood’s Boxborough farm by the town assessors, Aug. 24, 1821, and receipts and notes related to mortgage of the property, 1821-1827, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 95
    The assessors were Joseph Stone, Ephraim Robins, and Samuel Hayward.
  - Memorandum from register of probate concerning Concord real estate of the late John Meriam, April 16, 1822, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 96
  - Samuel Hoar’s certification about sale and ownership of the late John Meriam’s farm in Concord, April 14, 1823 and related document, undated, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 97
    It appears that Meriam’s widow sold the farm to Ebenezer Englesby, but that Samuel Hoar, superintendent of the farm, also benefited financially.
  - Manuscript excerpts from Worcester registry of deeds related to Horatio Carter and George Carter’s land titles in Lancaster, June 7, 1823, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 98
    Artemas Ward (1776-1850) was Registrar of Deeds and created this document.
  - Vote of Harvard Corporation to permit street construction on College land in Boston, March 7, 1825, and blank quit claim deed for this purpose, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 99
    The agreement was that the College would grant the City of Boston ownership of the part of the land on which the road was to be built.
  - Samuel Hoar’s receipt to Ebenezer Francis for John Meriam’s note and mortgage deed for Concord farm, March 23, 1827, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 100
  - Manuscript copy of deed of sale for marsh land in Cambridge to Edmund Monroe, Jan. 8, 1829, UAI 15.750 Box 8, Folder 37
    Munroe paid $700 for the land, which was given to Harvard by Royal Makepeace on April 24, 1824.
  - Manuscript copy of deed of sale for a “moiety or half part” of land in Charlestown to Edward Hearsey, March 31, 1829, UAI 15.750 Box 8, Folder 38
    Hearsey purchased the land for $315; it had been a gift to Harvard from Thomas Cary and had previously been owned by Samuel Cary.
  - Manuscript copy of deed of sale for land on Greenleaf’s wharf in Newburyport to Seth Sweetser, Dec. 29, 1829, UAI 15.750 Box 8, Folder 39
    The property was part of the Cary Estate. Sweetser paid $550 for it.
  - Manuscript copy of Thomas H. Darling’s deed for land in Concord, Lincoln, and Bedford, May 4, 1830, UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 101
    The land in Concord included John Meriam’s farm; this deed is for eight parcels of land.
Superseded call numbers
The call number for all material in the Records of land and property owned by Harvard University is now UAI 15.750. To assist researchers in identifying materials noted in previous citations, the list below provides references from obsolete call numbers to new box and folder numbers. Please use the current call number, UAI 15.750, with the appropriate box and folder number in place of the superseded call number when citing material from this collection.
Formerly part of UAI 15.300 Deeds records: seventeenth century series, 1650-1699
See UAI 15.750 Box 8, Folder 36. Deed of gift from John Newgate to Harvard College of £5 annually “for ever” from revenues of his Rumney Marsh farm, June 11, 1650
See UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 8. Deed of feoffment from John Coggan to Harvard College for Coggan’s Marsh, Jan. 16, 1654/5
See UAI 15.750 Box 7, Folder 86. Deed of gift from Theodore Atkinson to the President and Fellows of Harvard College for land near Boston, Oct. 13, 1671
See UAI 15.750 Box 8, Folder 7. Deed of gift from Samuel Ward to Harvard College for Ward’s Island,
See UAI 15.750 Box 9, Folder 18. Deed of mortgage for land near the Mill Bridge in Boston, from William Smith and Martha Smith to John Richards, (unknown month) 19, 1686/7
See UAI 15.750 Box 9, Folder 2. Deed of sale for 500 acres on Merriconeag Neck (Maine), from Joshua Scotton and Lydia Scotton to Samuel Sewall, March 29, 1690
See UAI 15.750 Oversize cabinet, Folder 1. Grant of 1,000 acres on Merriconeag Neck (Maine), issued by Massachusetts General Court to Samuel Sewall and Hannah Sewall, Nov. 8, 1693
See UAI 15.750 Box 9, Folder 16. Deed of gift of Narragansett farm from Samuel Sewall and Hannah Sewall to the President and Fellows of Harvard College, June 24, 1696
See UAI 15.750 Box 9, Folder 19. Deed of mortgage for land near Roxbury Gate in Boston, from Seth Perry and Dorothy Perry to John Richards, June 28, 1693
See UAI 15.750 Oversize cabinet, Folders 4 and 5. Leases of multiple lots in Framingham for 999 years, Thomas Danforth to Isaac Bowen, March 25, 1698
See UAI 15.750 Oversize cabinet, Folder 6. Lease of multiple lots in Framingham for 999 years, Thomas Danforth to John Whitney, March 25, 1699
Formerly UAI 15.310 Deeds records: eighteenth century series, 1738-1784 (inclusive)
See UAI 15.750 Oversize cabinet, Folder 9. Deed of sale for Waltham farm, Anthony Caverly to the President and Fellows of Harvard College, April 4, 1738
See UAI 15.750 Box 2, Folder 2. Deed of sale from Christopher Grant to the President and Fellows of Harvard College for 3½ acres of land adjacent to Hayward’s Pasture, March 19, 1757
See UAI 15.750 Box 2, Folder 56. Quitclaim deed for "Governor Pownall's lot" in Pownalborough, from Joseph Christophers to the President and Fellows of Harvard College, July 15, 1784
Formerly UAI 15.750 Lands Records: miscellaneous unbound records, 1683-1809
Materials formerly classified under this call number have been integrated into the appropriate series and are now found throughout the collection.
Formerly UAI 15.760 Lands Records: Rowley lands, 1704-1748
See UAI 15.750 Box 10, Folders 1-85.
Formerly UAI 15.765 Lands Records: Billerica Farm (Shawshin Farm), 1708-1779
See UAI 15.750 Box 12. These materials are not yet listed in the finding aid; they are severely mold-damaged and unavailable to researchers pending conservation treatment.
Formerly UAI 15.770 Lands Records: Bumpkin Island, 1696-1746
See UAI 15.750 Box 11, Folder 1-11. These materials, although listed in the finding aid, are severely mold-damaged and unavailable to researchers pending conservation treatment.
Formerly UAI 15.775 Lands Records: Collection of records, 1704-1830
Materials formerly classified under this call number have been integrated into the appropriate series and are now found throughout the collection. They include records related to properties in Newton, Rutland, Lunenburg, Townsend, Ward's Island, Coggan's Marsh, Stoughton's Marsh, the Gridley Estate, Stoughton's Pasture, Winchendon,Granby, the Webb Estate, the Pennoyer Estate, Hayward's Pasture, and the Waltham farm (Rogers Farm).
Formerly UAI 15.780 Lands Records: Merriconeag Neck, 1730-1773
These materials are not yet listed in the finding aid; they are severely mold-damaged and unavailable to researchers pending conservation treatment.
Formerly UAI 15.785 Lands Records: Narragansett Farm, 1731-1829
See UAI 15.750 Box 4, Folders 85-95
See UAI 15.750 Box 5, Folders 1-106
See UAI 15.750 Box 6, Folders 1-53
See UAI 15.750 Box 8, Folders 24-27
See UAI 15.750 Oversize cabinet, Folders 7 and 8
Formerly UAI 15.785.5 Lands Records: Narragansett Farm, unbound supplement, 1731-1775
See UAI 15.750 Box 11, Folders 12-16. These materials, although listed in the finding aid, are severely mold-damaged and unavailable to researchers pending conservation treatment.
Formerly UAI 15.790 Lands Records: Rogers Farm at Waltham, 1738-1779
See UAI 15.750 Box 11, Folders 17-65. These materials, although listed in the finding aid, are severely mold-damaged and unavailable to researchers pending conservation treatment.
Formerly UAI 15.795 Lands Records: Eastern lands (Maine), 1780-1835
See UAI 15.750 Box 2, Folders 23-103.
See UAI 15.750 Box 3, Folders 1-97.
See UAI 15.750 Box 4, Folders 1-63.
See UAI 15.750 Box 8, Folders 10-16.
See UAI 15.750 Box 9, Folders 3-15.
See UAI 15.750 Oversize cabinet, Folders 2 and 3.